<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-09-18T14:18:31+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Blackwood Gardens</title><subtitle>Designing Gardens of all shapes and sizes in East Lothian and Edinburgh</subtitle><author><name>Anna</name></author><entry><title type="html">Who does what in a Garden Renovation ?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/WhoDoesRenovation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who does what in a Garden Renovation ?" /><published>2025-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/WhoDoesRenovation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/WhoDoesRenovation"><![CDATA[<p>Do you know who to contact to renovate your garden?</p>

<p>Do you what services the various trades offer?</p>

<p>There are lots of professionals that work on and in a private garden; from designing it, to building it, and on to maintaining it.</p>

<p>Getting the right team can avoid costly mistakes, so you get the garden of your dreams.</p>

<h3 id="lets-start-with-a-garden-designer">Let’s start with a garden designer</h3>

<p>A garden designer is a <a href="https://sgld.org.uk/find-a-designer/working-with-a-designer">professional qualified in garden design.</a> (external link)</p>

<p>They will work with a client to fully understand their requirements to be able to design the garden to meet these requirements.</p>

<p>They will be able to produce scaled drawings of the garden from presentation plans to detailed drawings that will provide enough information for the landscaper to be able to build the garden.</p>

<p>They will select the materials and produce specifications for the build.</p>

<p>They will often work closely with the landscaper, monitoring the build stage to make sure the garden is built as designed.</p>

<p>Garden designers are knowledgeable on many aspects of the garden from lighting to drainage and will have horticulture skills to be able to select the right plants for your garden.</p>

<p>Their role is different to that of a landscape architect, who will often work on much larger projects such as urban landscapes, whereas Garden designers tend to work in private gardens and have detailed plant knowledge.</p>

<p>Planting design is a service many garden designers provide.</p>

<p>This is selecting plants combinations that will thrive in your garden and create the desired garden ambience.</p>

<p>Some designers just focus on planting design.</p>

<p>When selecting a garden designer it is important to understand the service they offer, the qualifications and experience they have and an understand if they have a particular style or philosophy to make sure they are a good fit for you.</p>

<p>Landscapers get your garden built.</p>

<p>Landscapers are the people who will deliver the built garden.</p>

<p>Landscapers are highly skilled trades people and will work with the different ground conditions and levels, build walls, lay patios, landscape the ground, install drainage, prepare the ground for planting and much much more.</p>

<p>They ususally don’t get involved in plant selection.</p>

<p>Before hiring a landscaper it is really important to know what you want built and the materials you want to use.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog%205,%20image%201%20garden%20under%20construction.jpg" alt="" />
<em>Garden under Construction</em></p>

<h3 id="horticulturist-or-gardener">Horticulturist or gardener?</h3>

<p>We have all heard of the term gardener, but there are many different levels of skills from amaturer  gardeners to highly trained and skilled horticulturists.</p>

<p>Horticulturists know their plants and how to look after them.</p>

<p>They understand the difference between a weed and a plant in the right place.</p>

<p>They can ID plants, know how and when to prune plants and much more.</p>

<p>Horticulturists are very different to gardeners who will only cut you grass or hedges and can’t tell the difference between say <em>Astrantia</em> and <em>Ajuga</em>.</p>

<p>Before hiring a gardener to look after your space, think about the tasks you want done, how often you need help and what you are willing to pay for ongoing maintenance.</p>

<p>It is a good idea to find out what other gardens they look after so you can get an ideas if its the right maintenance team for your needs.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog%205%20-%20image%202%20astrantia%20'Roma'.jpg" alt="" />
<em>Astrania Roma</em></p>

<p>There are many other professionals that work in private gardens from lawn care professionals to Arborists; who specialise in looking after trees and maintaining good tree health.</p>

<h3 id="choosing-who-to-work-with">Choosing who to work with</h3>

<p>Selecting who to work with is important.</p>

<p>Personal recommendations are a good place to start.</p>

<p>Also check out trade bodies, they will often list accredited members who adhere to professional standards.</p>

<p>It is always a good idea to see examples of work and ascertain skill levels and the service provided.</p>

<p>Communication will also be key to a successful working relationship, are they easy to get hold of, answer your questions and keep you informed of progress ?</p>

<p>If you are looking at a full garden transformation, then contact a garden designer in the first instance.</p>

<p>They will not only design your garden for you, but they will often bring in skilled and knowledgeable trades people at the different stages of the garden development.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog%205,%20image%203%20Anna%20setting%20out%20plants.JPG" alt="Anna and Plants" /></p>

<p>So if you are ready to start your garden transformation let’s start a conversation.</p>

<p>Anna Blackwood is the founder of Blackwood Gardens, a garden design studio based in East Lothian, operating across Edinburgh and the Lothians.</p>

<p>She is a keen plantswoman and enjoys transforming people’s gardens.</p>

<p>Anna is an associate member of the Society of Garden and Landscape Designers currently completing the final stages of accreditation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="chat" /><category term="chat" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Do you know who to contact to renovate your garden?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog5_cover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog5_cover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fragrant Garden</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Fragrant" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fragrant Garden" /><published>2025-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Fragrant</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Fragrant"><![CDATA[<p>Scent is so important in the garden.</p>

<p>Scent helps us connect with the garden on both an emotional and physical level.</p>

<p>Plants often evoke memories, and scent is a significant trigger for these memories.</p>

<p>For example, I remember my grandad growing sweetpeas (<em>lathyrus odoratus</em>) up an arch, so when I got my first garden, the first thing I did was grow sweetpeas up my arbour, bringing in a lovely sensory experience and the benefit of lots of cut flowers for the house too.</p>

<h2 id="fragrance-is-personal">Fragrance is personal</h2>

<p>What we like differs from person to person.</p>

<p>For example, one of my favourite scented plants is <em>Salvia ‘Nachtvilinder’</em>, but a colleague I worked with hated it.</p>

<p>I don’t like the smell of honey, so <em>Saracocca confusa</em> is not my favourite winter-scented shrub!</p>

<p>Give me a Daphne any time.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Blog8_Daphne_'Jacqueline_Postill'.jpg" alt="Daphne Jacqueline Postill" />
<em>Daphne ‘Jacqueline Postill’</em></p>

<h2 id="wake-up-and-smell-the-roses">Wake up and smell the roses</h2>

<p>We all know this common saying that encourages us to appreciate the beauty and simple pleasures in life.</p>

<p>Roses are one of the most infamous plants for scents, but not all modern roses are scented, so do your research when choosing a rose.</p>

<p>Visit a garden centre when they are in flower, so you can smell them and see the blooms. Don’t forget to check out the label too, so you know what type of rose you are buying and what their eventual size will become.</p>

<p>For example, ramblers can be huge; they are designed to grow up a tree, so take care when choosing to get the right rose for the right place.</p>

<p>You can always postpone the purchase until winter and buy a bare-root rose.</p>

<p>Winter is a good time to plant roses, and bare-root plants are often cheaper than a potted rose.</p>

<p>This <a href="https://www.davidaustinroses.co.uk/pages/fragrance-notes">Specialist Rose Grower (external link)</a> contains great information describing the different scents.</p>

<p>Roses have three scent categories:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Old Rose</li>
  <li>Tea</li>
  <li>Musk</li>
</ul>

<p>Enjoy researching your favourite scent.</p>

<p>The saying <strong>“Wake up and smell the roses”</strong> is a reminder to take notice of the world around us, so when you are pottering in your garden, you may notice the scent is not all about flowers.</p>

<p>You get some fabulous fragrant foliage, like the hard-working <em>geranium macrorrhizum</em> which makes a good ground cover plant, or the summer-flowering <em>agastache blackadder</em> with its tall blue spikes.</p>

<p>The leaves have a lovely fragrance with a purple underside.</p>

<p>Salvias have to be one of my favourites for scent, just brushing the foliage when weeding makes the task a joy as you get beautiful wafts of scent to reward your hard work.</p>

<h2 id="scent-for-all-seasons">Scent for all seasons</h2>

<p>A well-designed planting scheme will have seasonal interest in shape, form and colour and should plan for scent for all the seasons.</p>

<h3 id="winter">Winter</h3>
<p><em>Saracocca confusa</em> – often called Christmas box, <em>Daphne odorata</em> or <em>Osmanthus delvayi</em> are really good shrubs for scent, even <em>Galanthus nivalus</em> (snow drops) have a gentle scent you can enjoy, if you can get down close to enjoy it.</p>

<h3 id="spring">Spring</h3>
<p>Narcissus(daffodils) many have lovely scent e.g. ‘Artic bells’.</p>

<p>Hyacinth or <em>Convallaria majalis</em>(Lily of the valley) are good choices and <em>Phlox ‘Clouds of Perfume’</em> – well the name says it all.</p>

<p>Late spring and early summer the garden really starts to take off and there are lots of scented plants to choose from and this is when Paeonies really come into their own.</p>

<p>Paeonies are like Roses, you need to choose the cultivar carefully, as not all Paeonies have a gorgeous scent.</p>

<p>A few favourites for scent are: <em>Paeonia lactiflora ‘Duchess De Nemours’</em> or <em>Paeonia ‘Bowl of Beauty’</em> 
<img src="/assets/img/Blog8_Narcissus'Artic%20Bells'.jpg" alt="Artic Bells" />
<em>Narcissus bulbocodium ‘Artic Bells’</em></p>

<h3 id="summer">Summer</h3>
<p>The list of scented flowers in summer is just too long for this simple blog.</p>

<p>Of course you have all your old favourites like Phlox, Lavenders, Roses and Philadelphus.</p>

<p>Or you could try something different like <em>Cosmos atrosanguineus ‘Chocamocha’</em> (Chocolate Cosmos) and yes, it does smell of chocolate.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Blog8_Chocolate_cosmos.jpg" alt="Chocolate Cosmos" />
<em>Chocolate Cosmos</em></p>

<h3 id="autumn">Autumn</h3>
<p>Actaea not only has great foliage and pretty flowers, but it also has a lovely, gentle scent. <em>Calamintha nepeta</em> is loved by butterflies and bees and will flower from late summer into the autumn, again one to brush past and enjoy the smell.</p>

<h2 id="scents-for-different-types-of-plants">Scents for different types of plants:</h2>
<p>So many to choose from, but these are a good place to start:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Climbers</strong> Lonicera(honeysuckles), Roses, <em>Lathyrus odorata</em>(Sweet peas), <em>Wisteria sinensis</em></li>
  <li><strong>Shrubs</strong> Philadelphus, Osmanthus, Daphne, Roses, <em>Sambucus nigra</em></li>
  <li><strong>Herbs</strong> Lavender, Thyme, Rosemary, lemon balm</li>
  <li><strong>Perennials</strong> Phlox, Viola, Nepeta, Salvia</li>
  <li><strong>Bulbs</strong> Narcissus, <em>Hyacinthoides non-scripta</em>(native bluebell), <em>Convallaria majalis</em>(Lily of the valley),</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Blog_%208_Native_bluebell.jpg" alt="Bluebell" />
<em>Hyacinthoides non-scripta</em>(native bluebell)</p>

<p>Always check the plant label and description before buying plants to make sure it suits your garden, and better still, smell them to make sure you choose a scent you love.</p>

<h2 id="top-ten-picks-for-scent">Top ten picks for scent</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Blog8_Salvia'Nachtvilinder'.jpg" alt="Nachtvilinder" />
<em>Saliva ‘Nachtvilinder’</em></p>

<p>This is Anna’s personal top ten:</p>

<ol>
  <li><em>Salvia ‘Nachtvilinder’</em></li>
  <li><em>Daphne ‘Jacquiline Postill’</em></li>
  <li><em>Nepeta calamintha</em></li>
  <li><em>Paoenia ‘Bowl of Beauty’</em></li>
  <li><em>Rosa Rugosa</em></li>
  <li><em>Lathyrus odoreta</em></li>
  <li><em>Lavender ‘Hidcote’</em></li>
  <li><em>Phlox ‘Clouds of Perfume’</em></li>
  <li><em>Osmanthus x burkwoodii</em></li>
  <li><em>Sambucus nigra</em></li>
</ol>

<p>I hope I have inspired you to make a smelly garden that will give you pleasure and memories for years to come.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="chat" /><category term="chat" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Scent is so important in the garden.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog8_sweetpeas_cover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog8_sweetpeas_cover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We all love the seaside, but do our plants?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ChatCoastal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We all love the seaside, but do our plants?" /><published>2025-06-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ChatCoastal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ChatCoastal"><![CDATA[<p>Making a successful coastal garden is all about managing the conditions.</p>

<p>The main problem that faces a coastal garden is the wind, not only its strength and the drying effects this has on plants but also the salt carried in the wind.</p>

<p>Here are some tips for making the most of your coastal garden.</p>
<h2 id="create-shelter-belts">Create shelter belts</h2>

<p>Creating shelter belts in the garden will make a difference for you and the plants.</p>

<p>You can do this through stone walls, glass balustrades, hedges, fences, or careful placement of large rocks or shrubs.</p>

<p>This little bit of shelter can provide a place for you to sit out of the wind and shelter to help plants establish.</p>

<p>Pick materials that will last and weather, that also fit with the style of the garden and house.</p>

<p>A stone wall will last a lot longer than a wooden fence, which will also need regular protection.</p>

<p>If planting a hedge, pick your hedging plants that can cope with salty winds for example <em>escallonia</em> is a good choice for a hedge at the coast.</p>

<p>I have seen <em>escallonia</em> cope with the extreme winds of the Outer Hebrides.</p>

<h2 id="understand-your-climate">Understand your climate</h2>
<p>Coastal gardens in the UK often benefit from slightly milder winter temperatures than inland gardens, this can open up plants choices of less hardy plants like; <em>pittosporum</em>, or palms like <em>cordyline australis</em>.</p>

<h2 id="know-your-soil">Know your soil</h2>
<p>If your garden is really near the sea you may have very sandy soil, which is free draining. Sandy soils often leach nutrients, so make sure you know your soil type and choose plants that like those conditions.</p>

<p>Regular mulching is a great way to improve nutrients and moisture retention and dried seaweed is a great free resource for this.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog%202costal_Planting.jpg" alt="Lavandula and maritima" />
<em>Lavandula angustifolia, Crambe maritima with armeria maritima</em></p>

<p>Always pick plants that thrive in your soil types, so if you have free-draining sandy soil go for plants that will cope with dry conditions.</p>

<p>Plants such as <em>Erigeron</em> (sea holly) or even <em>Lavandula angustifolia</em> (lavender) both like it dry and can cope with windy conditions due to the glaucous (grey) foliage.</p>

<h2 id="choose-salt-tolerant-plants">Choose salt-tolerant plants</h2>
<p>Research plants that will cope with a coastal situation, and observe which plants thrive in your neighbour’s gardens.</p>

<p>Plants that often do well are plants that have coping methods for wind.</p>

<p>Grasses do well in coastal gardens as well as <em>Cortaderia selloanna</em> (pampas grass) and <em>Phormiums</em>.</p>

<p>Pines also cope with windy conditions as do some other coniferous shrubs.</p>

<p>Perennials such as <em>Crocosmia</em>, <em>Achilliea</em> and <em>Phlomis</em> are all good perennials for windy locations.</p>

<p>Another option for windy conditions is to choose low-growing alpine plants, as their growth habitat makes them better at coping with the conditions. 
For example, <em>Armeria maritima</em> (sea thrift) is ideal.</p>

<p>Some bulbs will also do well at the coast like <em>narcissus</em> (daffodil).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog%202_costal_armeria.jpg" alt="Almeria Maritima" />
<em>Armeria maritima</em></p>

<p>With a little bit of research, or help from a professional garden designer you can make a beautiful coastal garden by picking the right materials and plants to enjoy your coastal garden location.</p>

<p>Blackwood Gardens is a garden design studio in East Lothian. Anna is the founder and designer at Blackwood Gardens, she has a wide horticulture knowledge and loves the sea, having been brought up in a coastal town and spent a lot of time on the water sailing.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="chat" /><category term="chat" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Making a successful coastal garden is all about managing the conditions.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog%202_costal_rosa.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog%202_costal_rosa.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Creating Pet Friendly Gardens</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ChatPets" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating Pet Friendly Gardens" /><published>2025-04-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ChatPets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ChatPets"><![CDATA[<p>Designing your new dream garden needs to consider the wants and needs of the whole family including your furry friends.</p>

<p>After all our pets are part of our family, and our garden is an extension of our home.</p>

<p>A good place to start is thinking about your pet’s needs and their character and how you want to use the garden as a whole family.</p>

<p>For example, do you want to have a beautiful planting area that excludes the pets or would they prefer to choose plants that are robust and can cope with a bit of trampling from, say, a bouncy dog, like the lovely ‘Fern’ ?</p>

<p>There are many many poisonous plants in gardens, many of which your pet will naturally avoid, as we humans do too, but it is good to know which plants are toxic to pets, and these can be avoided.</p>

<p>When choosing plants – the plant label will often state this but do some research online.</p>

<p>Sites such as ‘Gardeners World’ state if they are toxic to pets, as will The Royal Horticultural Society.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog6_img2_toxic.JPG" alt="toxicplants" />
<em>Information from the ‘Gardeners World’ website showing plant toxicity</em></p>

<h3 id="dogs">Dogs</h3>
<p>Dogs come in all shapes and sizes.</p>

<p>Some like to dig, others are chasers, there are barkers and those who just enjoy sitting in the sun getting their tummy tickled.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Blog6_%20img3_Fern2.jpeg" alt="FernTheDog" /></p>

<p>How does your dog behave?</p>

<p>Are they old, young, curious, and/or well-trained?</p>

<p>How your dog behaves will be a factor in the design solution for the garden.</p>

<p>For example, raised beds may work as a deterrent for small or older dogs to stop them from going in your flower beds.</p>

<p>Do you want specific parts of the garden for a dog play or exercise space where you can have toys for entertainment and exercise.</p>

<p>Does the garden need to be enclosed to stop a pet escape ?</p>

<p>Would you like a source of clean drinking water for your dog, or an outdoor shower area so muddy pets can be cleaned before entering the house?</p>

<p>These are some typical considerations when planning a dog-friendly garden.</p>

<p>Lawns are one of the big areas that get damaged by dogs, either through constant wear and tear from running, digging, or damage from urine.</p>

<p>If your dog likes to dig, think about creating an area specific to them for digging.</p>

<p>If they run the same way every time, say along a track, consider putting in moveable obstacles so they have to vary their running route.</p>

<p>To reduce the damage to your lawn from urine, rinse the area with water.</p>

<p>You can also get products to treat the area and neutralise it.</p>

<p>Better still, where possible train the dog to use a dedicated discrete place and protect the rest of the lawn.</p>

<h4 id="dogs-and-plants">Dogs and plants</h4>

<p>Do your research, before selecting plants. The <a href="https://www.dogstrust.org.uk/dog-advice/health-wellbeing/at-home/poisonous-plants">Dog Trust</a> has a helpful list:</p>

<h3 id="cats">Cats</h3>

<p>Cats love to explore and hide, so having trees and bushes is a good idea giving them climbing places and hidey spaces.</p>

<p>You could also try planting textural grasses that cast shadows and move in the wind, for a bit of extra fun.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog6_img4_grasses.jpg" alt="Grasses" /></p>

<p>The bark of trees or even a rough log are perfect for cats to use as scratching posts and don’t forget the clean drinking water.</p>

<p>If you like to see birds in the garden, be careful where you place bird feeders, not near bushes where the cat can hide and pounce.</p>

<p>You could also put obstacles on the post to make it hard for the cat to climb.</p>

<h4 id="plants-and-cats">Plants and cats</h4>

<p>There are numerous plants that cats like and are attracted to.</p>

<p>The most famous one is <em>Nepeta</em>, commonly known as catnip.</p>

<p>Cats love the smell and rolling in it, so make sure you plant some.</p>

<p>It will also attract bees to the garden.</p>

<p>There are many plants that are toxic to cats such as narcissus (daffodils).</p>

<p>Alliums and all lilies are poisonous to cats.</p>

<p>Luckily most cats are fussy eaters and will avoid them, but it’s good to know what is dangerous to your cat.</p>

<p>So do some research before choosing plants for the garden.</p>

<p>Organisations like the Cat Protection League can provide helpful information.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://hta.org.uk/potentiallyharmfulplants">Horticultural Trades Association</a> provides information on toxic plants to pets and humans.</p>

<h3 id="pet-friendly-gardens">Pet-friendly Gardens</h3>
<p>Creating a garden for you and your pets is a challenge, but worth it!</p>

<p>Like all design challenges it is about making the garden work for all the family and by considering your pets in the planning of your garden, so it is safe, fun, and rewarding.</p>

<p>That way the whole family will benefit by keeping your furry friends happy.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="chat" /><category term="chat" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Designing your new dream garden needs to consider the wants and needs of the whole family including your furry friends.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/Blog6%20_Fern_headshot.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/Blog6%20_Fern_headshot.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Love your garden to sell your home</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/GardentoSell" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love your garden to sell your home" /><published>2025-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/GardentoSell</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/GardentoSell"><![CDATA[<p>Purchasing a new home is an emotional affair as it is often our largest financial commitment so getting it right is a big deal.</p>

<p>Sound purchase decisions are required to make sure your new house meets all your criteria.</p>

<p>Get that all right and it may still not be the right house for you, you need to fall in love with it.</p>

<p>Falling in love with your future home starts before you even enter the house and the garden is a big part of that all-important first impression.</p>

<p>Here are some tips and advice to make the best use of your garden when selling your home.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-see-when-you-look-out-of-the-window">What do you see when you look out of the window?</h2>

<p>Stand back and look out the window- what do you see?</p>

<p>Have you created an attractive view from your window or are you looking at garden clutter?</p>

<p>Do you see wheelie bins, plastic toys or the back of a shed ?</p>

<p>Tidy up, put bins in a discreet place or screen it with a trellis and evergreen climber.</p>

<p>A well-appointed shrub, sculpture or water feature can provide added interest, acting as a focal point to direct your eye and enhance the view from the window.</p>

<h3 id="dont-reveal-everything-at-once">Don’t reveal everything at once</h3>
<p>Secret spaces in gardens are great. They can be playful and can reveal themselves gradually.</p>

<p>A potential buyer wandering around your garden would be delighted to discover a garden room, a hidden vegetable plot or a secluded seat.</p>

<h3 id="work-your-boundaries">Work your boundaries</h3>

<p>Garden boundaries are a key part of the garden.</p>

<p>Try softening hard landscaping such as walls and fences with climbers which can help blend it in with the surrounding landscape rather than creating a hard edge which can feel like an abrupt finish to the space.</p>

<p>If you have hedges make sure they are neatly trimmed.</p>

<p>Overgrown shrubs and hedges can take up a lot of space and make your garden feel smaller, so give them a good cut back and show the garden is loved.</p>

<h3 id="tidy-up">Tidy up</h3>

<p>The same goes for the garden as the house, cut your grass (unless it is an intentional meadow), edge your borders - it makes a big difference.</p>

<p>Weed your plant borders and if you have any gaps you can always fill them with some extra plants (summer annuals are a great way to do this quickly and cheaply), you don’t want to be able to see the soil.</p>

<p>Weed gravel areas, sweep paths, lift leaves from paths and lawns, and remove moss and algae from paths patios and decks so they are not slippery.</p>

<p>Cut hedges, and prune shrubs – especially evergreen structural shrubs as these are the backbone to other planting schemes.
<img src="/assets/img/Blog%203,%20image%202,%20Garden%20focal%20point.jpg" alt="Focal Point" /></p>

<h3 id="think-about-colour-and-scent">Think about colour and scent</h3>

<p>The type and style of garden you have will depend on the type of planting you have selected. For example, a bright colourful garden is welcoming, whereas an evergreen garden is calming, try to stick to one style of planting and think about the impression you want to give.</p>

<p>Scent evokes memories – so choose plants that provide pleasant smells to keep your garden front of mind. Lavender, nepetia or salvia are all good at path edges as they release the scent as you brush past.</p>

<p>Jasmine, honeysuckle or a climbing rose is good on a trellis which can be enjoyed without having to bend down.</p>

<h3 id="pots--less-is-more">Pots – less is more</h3>

<p>My golden rule with pots is less is more, go big and keep to a limited style and colour.</p>

<p>Lots of little pots of all different styles look cluttered.</p>

<p>Pots on either side of a path is a formal look which can lead you in that direction, it often works well at the top of steps.</p>

<p>One single pot at the end of the path acts as a focal point and a group of three pots works well as a collection in an area of hard landscaping.</p>

<p>If you need to buy new pots remember you can take always take them with you to your new house.
<img src="/assets/img/Blog%203,%20image%203,plant%20pot%20arrangement.jpg" alt="Plant Pots arrangement" /></p>

<h4 id="last-thing">Last thing</h4>

<p>If you aren’t a gardener and your garden is a blank canvas – then keep it that way, keep it clean and tidy and if the potential new buyer is a gardener they will see the potential of all that lovely space!</p>

<h3 id="happy-house-selling">Happy house selling.</h3>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="chat" /><category term="chat" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Purchasing a new home is an emotional affair as it is often our largest financial commitment so getting it right is a big deal.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/Blog%203,%20image%201,%20Broughton%20House%20Garden.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/Blog%203,%20image%201,%20Broughton%20House%20Garden.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Garden Lessons</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Chat-Five-Lessons" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Garden Lessons" /><published>2025-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Chat%20Five%20Lessons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Chat-Five-Lessons"><![CDATA[<h3 id="if-only-i-had-known">If only I had known…</h3>
<p><em>I could have saved myself a lot of time, money and energy</em></p>

<p>We can apply this scenario to lots of our life experiences.</p>

<p>This time I am talking about your garden and turning it into your dream garden.</p>

<p>How do we avoid some of those mistakes?</p>

<p>Well here are some tips for you…</p>

<h2 id="ground-prep-is-key">Ground prep is key</h2>
<p>Don’t take shortcuts.</p>

<p>More work now means less later.</p>

<p>Whether you are rejuvenating an old border or creating a new border, preparing the ground for planting is key.</p>

<p>This includes removing any perennial weeds, digging out old roots (cutting back will often see them come back bigger), getting rid of compaction, removing large 
stones, and, if needed, improving the fertility of the soil.</p>

<h2 id="know-your-soil-and-work-with-the-conditions">Know your soil and work with the conditions.</h2>
<p>The old saying ‘right plant in the right place’ is the right saying!</p>

<p>I meet people all the time who try and grow plants they like in the wrong conditions and it just results in sad straggly plants or dead experiments, poor owners and a garden dream that isn’t realised.</p>

<p>If you have heavy clay soil that stays cold and wet in the winter and compacted in the summer you should choose plants that can cope with those conditions.</p>

<h2 id="where-is-the-sun">Where is the sun?</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/img/blog%204,%20image%201%20compass.jpg" alt="Compass" /></p>

<p>Which way does your garden face?</p>

<p>How much sun does the garden get a day?</p>

<p>Is your garden getting full sun; over 6 hours a day, or is it in partial shade or even full shade?</p>

<p>How windy is it?</p>

<p>Observing your garden conditions is important to choosing the plants that like the conditions you have.</p>

<p>You may get away with a shady plant in a sunny position, but not the other way around.</p>

<h2 id="less-is-more">Less is more</h2>
<p>Don’t cram the plants in.</p>

<p>They need space to grow.</p>

<p>You will be surprised how bare a newly planted border looks, but believe me those gaps will soon disappear, so don’t feel tempted to ignore the plant label and squeeze in an extra plant.</p>

<p>If your border is overplanted it could impact the plants’ health with reduced vigour of the plants.</p>

<p>You will also have spent too much money on plants and it won’t be long before you will need to remove extra plants, or split and divide existing plants to keep 
them in check, which is all extra money and effort.</p>

<p>If you don’t like seeing a few bare patches as the planting develops, then pop in some annuals for instant colour, they won’t last the winter and will fill up the gaps in the short term.
<img src="/assets/img/blog%204,%20image%202,%20new%20border%20planting.jpg" alt="New planting spaced evenly" /></p>

<h2 id="your-plant-label-is-your-friend">Your plant label is your friend</h2>
<p>If you are buying plants from a reputable garden centre or plant nursery your plants will be clearly labelled with the full plant name.</p>

<p>It will tell you the conditions the plant likes to grow in and it will tell you the ultimate height and spread of the plant.</p>

<p>So if the label says 200cm – it will grow 2 meters high!</p>

<p>If the spread says 600cm, then that is how far apart you need to have the plant from its neighbour.</p>

<p>This might all sound like a lot of work and effort and you may not want to spend time on the “trial and error” approach. Maybe you would prefer to have an expert help you plan your garden and avoid some mistakes…</p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="chat" /><category term="chat" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If only I had known… I could have saved myself a lot of time, money and energy]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog%204,%20image%203%20plant%20label.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog%204,%20image%203%20plant%20label.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Front and Back Garden Dunfermline</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Dunfermline" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Front and Back Garden Dunfermline" /><published>2023-04-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Dunfermline</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Dunfermline"><![CDATA[<h2 id="back-garden">Back garden</h2>
<p>The brief was to improve access around the garden as it had awkward steps, a steep planting bank, slippery deck and rough gravel paths. The owner is a keen gardener and wanted lots of space for planting, a wildlife pond and space to grow vegetables. They also wanted a new seating area with a combined shed/greenhouse building and summerhouse.</p>

<p>The design uses lots of organic shapes and curves, featuring a smooth resin bound path which provides easy access around the garden.  A beautiful curved paddlestone wall separates upper and lower planting terraces. The central pond can be viewed from the house as well as from the summerhouse. The design includes a new porcelain patio and raised beds for growing veg. All the utilities are screened in the side passage.
<img src="/assets/img/TerraceDunfermline.jpg" alt="Terrace" />
<em>Terrace Planting with Curved Paddlestone Wall</em>
<img src="/assets/img/BG_Projects_Dunfermline_pond.jpg" alt="Wildlife friendly pond" />
<em>Wildlife Friendly Pond</em>
<img src="/assets/img/DunfermlineBackdoor.jpg" alt="Terrace" />
<em>New back door steps, resin path, raised beds and greenhouse</em></p>

<blockquote>

</blockquote>

<h2 id="front-garden">Front Garden</h2>
<p>Replaced the existing driveway with a new resin bound gravel drive (SUDs compliant) edged with setts. The lawn was replaced with new rabbit proof planting in the front garden. The front connects to the back garden through the use of materials and provides a wow factor as you enter the house.
<img src="/assets/img/DunfermlineFront.jpg" alt="Front" />
<em>New Drive and Planting</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/BG%20_Projects_Dunfermline_front2.jpg" alt="rabbit proof plants" />
<em>rabbit proof planting</em></p>

<h2 id="site-before-starting">Site Before Starting</h2>
<p><img src="assets/img/DunfermlineBefore.jpg" alt="Before" />
<em>Back garden uneven paving and slippery deck</em></p>

<p><img src="assets/img/DunfermlineBefore2.jpg" alt="SideBefore" />
<em>Back garden pavers and awkward levels</em></p>

<p><img src="assets/img/DunfermlineFrontBefore.jpg" alt="FrontBefore" />
<em>Front garden before</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="projects" /><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back garden The brief was to improve access around the garden as it had awkward steps, a steep planting bank, slippery deck and rough gravel paths. The owner is a keen gardener and wanted lots of space for planting, a wildlife pond and space to grow vegetables. They also wanted a new seating area with a combined shed/greenhouse building and summerhouse.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/SweetPeaDunfermline.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/SweetPeaDunfermline.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Front Garden - Edinburgh</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Portobello" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Front Garden - Edinburgh" /><published>2023-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Portobello</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Portobello"><![CDATA[<h3 id="portobello-front-garden">Portobello Front Garden</h3>
<p>This project was about the rejuvination of a front garden in the conservation area of Portobello. 
The garden was made up of lawn, mature shrubs and concrete paths with bins on view. The owner wanted to replace the paths, hide the bins and create a garden that gave doorstep appeal. As this garden is located in a conservation area planning permission was secured to make the changes.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/BG_Projects_portobello_front.jpg" alt="portobello" />
<em>Plant Rich Front Garden</em>
<img src="assets/img/BG_projects_portobello_front3.jpg" alt="portobello" />
<em>Welcoming Space</em>
<img src="/assets/img/porty6.jpg" alt="portobello" />
<em>Garden in Autumn new path and binstore</em></p>

<p>The concrete path was changed to riven sandstone and edged with cropped setts. The bins were relocated into a new bin store away from the front of the house and a purpose made bench was added at the front door.</p>

<p>Many of the shrubs were retained and relocated during the build. The muddy lawns were replaced with gravel planting, giving the garden more colour, texture and biodiversity.</p>

<p>The materials were selected to compliment the house and area with  planting selected for its coastal location.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/porty3.jpg" alt="portobello" /><em>Achillea and Eryngium – coastal planting</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Anna made the whole process of changing our garden incredibly straightforward. She worked very collaboratively and creatively on the designs, taking the time to really understand our requirements before overseeing the landscapers and ensuring they delivered the work to a really high standard. Her choice of plants went way beyond anything we’d have done ourselves and look fantastic. Highest recommendation!”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="assets/img/BG_Projects_portobello _ Echinops.jpg" alt="portobello Echinops" />
<em>Echinops and Achillea</em></p>

<h2 id="site-before-starting">Site Before Starting</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/img/portybefore1.jpg" alt="portobello" /><em>Before - Muddy lawn with visible bins</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/portydigger.jpg" alt="portobello" /><em>Digger during the build</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="projects" /><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Portobello Front Garden This project was about the rejuvination of a front garden in the conservation area of Portobello. The garden was made up of lawn, mature shrubs and concrete paths with bins on view. The owner wanted to replace the paths, hide the bins and create a garden that gave doorstep appeal. As this garden is located in a conservation area planning permission was secured to make the changes.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/BG_projects_portobello_front2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/BG_projects_portobello_front2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Planting Design - Edinburgh</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Balerno" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Planting Design - Edinburgh" /><published>2023-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Balerno</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Balerno"><![CDATA[<p>Planting Design – Edinburgh</p>

<p>This large modern garden was newly designed and landscaped when Blackwood Gardens  was brought in to do the planting design. The owners wanted low maintenance planting with texture and topiary to compliment and soften the hard landscaping materials.</p>

<p>The planting was designed with structural hornbeam pillars,  topiary evergreen shrubs and  specimen trees underplanted with textural grasses. The back border consisted of only white flowers and a  limited warm colour palette was used in the rest of the garden. Key plants were repeated to give the garden rhythm and  unity.</p>

<p>The planting is still maturing and images shown are in their first year. Mature trees and shrubs were used to help establish the garden.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Balerno2.jpg" alt="Planting Design Edinburgh Garden" />
<em>Hornbeam Pillar with Carex Grasses</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Balerno3.jpg" alt="Planting Design Edinburgh Garden" />
<em>Hydrangea ‘Limelight’</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Balerno4.jpg" alt="Planting Design Edinburgh Garden" />
<em>View of New Planting</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/BalernoSketch.jpg" alt="Edinburgh Garden Sketch" />
<em>Edinburgh Garden Sketch</em></p>

<h2 id="site-before-starting">Site Before Starting</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/img/BalernoBefore.jpg" alt="Edinburgh Garden Sketch" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="projects" /><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Planting Design – Edinburgh]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/Balerno1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/Balerno1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cockenzie East Lothian</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Cockenzie" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cockenzie East Lothian" /><published>2023-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Cockenzie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Cockenzie"><![CDATA[<h2 id="sunny-coastal-garden">Sunny Coastal Garden</h2>
<p>This sunny enclosed garden is located in a conservation area of a historic fishing village in East Lothian. The owner wanted to increase the size of the seating area, while keeping it in the same location. The challenge was the house was accessed by  doors on different levels.</p>

<p>The client also wanted to  increase their privacy as the garden was overlooked  from a neighbouring property.</p>

<p>Broken paving was to be replaced and the owner wanted lots of plants and loved colour.</p>

<p>Planning permission was secured prior to the build starting.</p>

<p>The solution to the seating area was a new millboard composite deck on one level making the seating area accessible from different doors of the house. A larch wall topper was added for extra privacy to the old garden walls. 
<img src="/assets/img/cockenzie_after1.jpg" alt="East Lothian Coastal Garden" />
<em>Curved Millboard composite deck, new sandstone paths with water feature</em></p>

<p>The broken concrete paving was lifted, crushed  and reused on site as hardcore below new sandstone paths.</p>

<p>The lawn was replaced with a large planting bed full of colourful perennials and small shrubs with a feature water bowl. 
<img src="/assets/img/cockenzie_after2.jpg" alt="East Lothian Coastal Garden" />
<em>Newly planted area</em></p>

<p>Many of the original plants were retained and replanted.</p>

<p>A small gravel  planting area was introduced so it could double up as an area for drying washing, making this small garden not only beautiful but also practical.</p>

<p>Garden images are of planting in first year with planting still to mature.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/cockenzie_after3.jpg" alt="East Lothian Coastal Garden" />
<em>Larch Wall topper added for privacy</em>
<img src="/assets/img/BG_Projects_cockenzie_costal planting.jpg" alt="East Lothian Coastal" />
<em>Coastal Planting</em>
<img src="/assets/img/BG_Projects_cockenzie_path.jpg" alt="East Lothian Coastal Plants" />
<em>Edge Planting Softening Paths</em></p>
<h2 id="site-before-starting">Site Before Starting</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/img/cockenzie_before.jpg" alt="East Lothian Coastal Garden" />
<em>Site before: broken paving - patio too small - overlooked by neighbours</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Anna</name></author><category term="projects" /><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sunny Coastal Garden This sunny enclosed garden is located in a conservation area of a historic fishing village in East Lothian. The owner wanted to increase the size of the seating area, while keeping it in the same location. The challenge was the house was accessed by doors on different levels.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/cockenzie_after4.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/cockenzie_after4.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>